William B. Bradbury Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
William B. Bradbury Collection1846-1928 (bulk 1847-1862)
ML31.B7
Bradbury, William B. (William Batchelder), 1816-1868
circa 40 items 3 boxes 1 linear foot
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Bradbury's secular music is represented by published vocal scores, some in photocopy, and probable holograph of Song of the South. Contains an album compiled by Bradbury in Europe (1847-1849) of autograph musical sketches by Franz Abt, Niels Gade, Joseph Joachim, Jenny Lind, Albert Lortzing, Giacomo Meyerbeer, Ignaz Moscheles, Clara Schumann, Robert Schumann, Louis Spohr, Richard Wagner, and others; sketches by Felix Mendelssohn, Walter Damrosch, and Ignace Paderewski added later. Photographs, clippings, printed and ms. music by other composers, correspondence, Bradbury's baton, etc. also are included.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Abt, Franz, 1819-1885--Autographs.; Bradbury, William B. (William Batchelder), 1816-1868--Correspondence.; Bradbury, William B. (William Batchelder), 1816-1868.; Bradbury, William B. (William Batchelder), 1816-1868.; Bradbury, William B. (William Batchelder), 1816-1868. Song of the south.; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950--Autographs.; Gade, Niels W. (Niels Wilhelm), 1817-1890--Autographs.; Joachim, Joseph, 1831-1907--Autographs.; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887--Autographs.; Lortzing, Albert, 1801-1851--Autographs.; Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847--Autographs.; Meyerbeer, Giacomo, 1791-1864--Autographs.; Moscheles, Ignaz, 1794-1870--Autographs.; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941--Autographs.; Schumann, Clara, 1819-1896--Autographs.; Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856--Autographs.; Spohr, Louis, 1784-1859--Autographs.; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883--Autographs.
Subjects
Musical sketches.; Musicians--Autographs.; Musicians--Correspondence.
Titles
Bradbury collection, 1846-1928
Administrative Information
Provenance
Donated by Joan M. Undeland, the composer's great-great-granddaughter, 1976.
Additional materials donated by Joan M. Undeland, the composer's great-great-granddaughter, 2000.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The William B. Bradbury Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1816 October 6 Born William Batchelder Bradbury in York, Maine
1830 Family moves to Boston Bradbury studies with Sumner Hill Attends Lowell Mason's Boston Academy of Music Sings in Mason's Boudoin Street Church Choir
1830s Works as an organist and teacher
1840 Becomes music director of the First Baptist Church in Brooklyn, New York
1840s Introduces the teaching of singing into New York City public schools
1841 Becomes music director of Baptist Tabernacle of New York; begins to teach children's singing in a similar style to that of Mason's school in Boston The Young Choir (compiled with Thomas Hastings) is published
1847-49 Studies piano, singing, harmony, and composition in Europe
1849 Returns to United States; continues to teach, compose, and compile collections of hymns
1854 Forms Bradbury Piano Company with his brother, Edward G.Bradbury, and Light and Newton, the German piano manufacturers
1858 Music collection, The Jubilee, is published, selling over 200,000 copies
1861 Music collection, The Golden Chain, is published, selling 2,000,000 copies
1867 Music collection, Fresh Laurels, is published, selling 1,200,000 copies
1868 Jan. 7 Dies in Montclair, New Jersey
Scope and Content Note
The William B. Bradbury Collection was given to the Library of Congress in 1976 and 2000 by Joan M. Undeland, Bradbury's great-great-granddaughter. These materials complemented a number of Bradbury's holograph and first-edition printed musical scores that were given to the Library of Congress by Hubert P. Main and others earlier in the 20th century.
Notable in the collection is an autograph musical sketchbook that Bradbury compiled between 1847 and 1849 when he was studying in Europe. This sketchbook contains short musical sketches by some of Bradbury's contemporaries, including Franz Abt, Niels Gade, Joseph Joachim, Jenny Lind, Albert Lorzing, Giacomo Meyerbeer, Ignaz Moscheles, Clara Schumann, Robert Schumann, Louis Spohr, Marianne Spohr, Richard Wagner, and others. Sketches by Felix Mendelssohn, Walter Damrosch, Ignaz Paderewski and Felix Mendelssohn were added later. The album also contains two non-musical entries, a watercolor sketch by Susette Hauptmann, and a letter to Bradbury from Felix Mendelssohn that C. F. Becker added to the album in 1849.
All of the compositions by Bradbury in the collection are secular, even though he composed over 800 hymn-tunes. One of these works, Bradbury's Song of the south, may be in his own hand.
An unpublished biography entitled "William B. Bradbury, His Life and Times" that was written by his granddaughter, Elma Marvin, and a biographical letter written in 1928 by Bradbury's son are also found in the collection. A letterpress book in the collection contains correspondence relative to Bradbury's music publications during the early 1860s.
Photographs in the collection include those of Bradbury, his wife, Ada Esther Fessender Bradbury, and his piano, which was manufactured by his company, Light, Newton & Bradbury.
The status of the literary rights of the unpublished materials in the William B. Bradbury Collection is unknown.
Organization of the William B. Bradbury Collection
The William B. Bradbury Collection is organized in 7 series:
Biographical Materials
Music
Letterpress Book
Album
Photographs
Clippings
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/95702388
Container List
- Biographical Materials (Box 2)
  The Biographical Materials series consists of writings about William B. Bradbury, his family, and his music.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by title or subject.
  - Anonymous. Family Recollections. (Box 2)
  - Anonymous. "Notes on a Musical Autograph Collection once Owned by William Batchelder Bradbury." (Box 2)
  - Bradbury, William L. to [?]. Letter dated Sept. 28, 1928. (Box 2)
  - Marvin, Elma. "William B. Bradbury: his life and times." Unpublished biography, [photocopy] (Box 2)
  - William B. Bradbury, his life and times and some family history, unpublished biography, compiled by Elma Marvin (Box 3)
- Music (Box 1, Box 3)
  The Music series is represented by three subseries: Bradbury as Composer; Brabury as Hymn Writer; Other Composers and Arrangers. The series consists of printed and holograph manuscripts.
  Arrangment is alphabetical by composer and title.
  - Bradbury as Composer
    - Esther, the beautiful queen, a cantata or short oratorio. New York: Mason Brothers, 1856. (Box 3)
    - Flag of our union, The. New York: Firth, Pond, & Co., 1861., Printed piano-vocal score; Words by George P. Morris, Esq.; "New and Correct Edition" (Box 1)
    - Sing to me, mother. New York: C. M. Tremaine, 1867., Printed piano-vocal score; "To Mrs. Frank Dodge" (Box 1)
    - Song of the south., Holograph vocal score; SATB (Box 1)
    - "Tea Party" song, A. New York: Newman & Ivison, 1852., Photocopy of printed vocal score; SATB (Box 1)
    - There's a sound among the forest trees. New York: [s.n.], 1864., Printed piano-vocal score; Words by Fanny Crosby (Box 1)
    - Great convention, or woman's rights, The. New York: Newman & Ivison, 1852., Photocopy of printed vocal score; SATB; Arranged from a celebrated German people's song "Words written for this Work by a Lady" (Box 1)
    - Jenny Lind mania, The. New York: Newman & Ivison, 1852., Photocopy of printed vocal score; SATB; Arranged from a popular melody; Words by W. H. C. West (Box 1)
    - Star-spangled banner, The. [S.l.]: Bigelow & Main, 1870., Photocopy of printed vocal score; SATB (Box 1)
  - Badbury as hymn writer (Box 3)
    - The Bradbury Trio: comprising New Golden Chain, New Golden Shower, and New Golden Censer. New York: Biglow and Main, 1870. (Box 3)
    - Bright jewels for the Sunday school; a new collection of Sunday school songs written expressly for this work; many of which are the latest compositions of William B. Bradbury / Rob't Lowry; editor; assisted by Wm. F. Sherwin and Chester G. Allen. New York: Biglow & Main, 1869., Also publsihed by Ivison, Phinney, Blakeman & Co. (Box 3)
    - Metropolitan Glee Book; or, Alpine Glee Singer, volume second. A new collection of glee choruses, opera choruses, and four-part songs, from the most popular authors, to which is added the most favorite choruses from Handel's oratorio of the Messiah / by William B. Bradbury. New York: Newman and Ivison, 1852. (Box 3)
  - Other Composers and Arrangers (Box 3)
    - By Composer (Box 3)
      - Dyer, S. O.
        - Spider and the fly, The. New York: C. H. Holt, 1847., Printed piano-vocal score; SATB; Words by Jesse Hutchinson, Jr. (Box 3)
      - Mendelssohn, Felix
        - [Three motets, op. 69]., Ms. vocal score; SATB; Includes: No. 1, Lord, now lettest Thou thy Servant No. 2, O be joyful in the Lord No. 3, My Soul doth magnify the Lord (Box 3)
        - [Volkslied]. Berlin: Schlesinger, n.d., Printed piano-vocal score; duet; Includes: "Wasserfahrt," No. 3; Pl. S. 2091 (3) (Box 3)
      - Mozart, W. A.
        - Eheliche gute Nacht. Leipzig: Breitkopf, n.d., Printed piano-vocal score (Box 3)
      - Schubert, Franz
        - [Du bist die Ruh]. Boston: George P. Reed & Co., n.d., Printed piano-vocal score; "Thou Art the Rest," in Gems of German Songs; J. S. Dwight, trans. (Box 3)
      - Wyman, B. and G. P. Newell
        - [Library of sacred music]. New York: Wyman and Newell, 1846., Organ-vocal score; SATB; Printed anthology of sacred choral music (Box 3)
    - By Title (Box 3)
      - Hymns and songs of praise [3 volumes]. New York: Anson D. F. Randolph and Company, 1874. (Box 3)
      - Gospel Hymns, Consolidated. New York: Biglow and Main, 1883. (Box 3)
      - Northfield Hymnal. Chicago: Biglow and Main, 1904. (Box 3)
- Letterpress Book, February 1861-July 1862 (Box 1, Box 2)
  The Letterpress Book series consists primarly of correspondence relative to Bradbury's music publications during the early 1860s.
  Arrangement is chronological by date.
  - Bound holograph letterpress book with business correspondence, Feb. 1861-July 1862 (Box 1)
  - Pencil transcriptions of letterpress book in steno notebooks. Typed transcription of six letters from letterpress book (Box 2)
- Album (Box 1)
  The Album series consists of one bound volume containing holograph music sketches, one letter, and signatures of 19th-century composers.
  Arrangement is by format.
  - Album containing holograph music sketches, one letter, and signatures of 19th-century composers and others; includes autographs of: Franz Abt, C. F. Becker, Ferdinand Böhme, Walter Damrosch, Ferdinand David, Niels W. Gade, Greissiger, Susette Hauptmann, Hermann Huegeli, Joseph Joachim, C. Klingemann, Hermann Langer, Jenny Lind, Albert Lortzing, F. Mendel, Giacomo Meyerbeer, Ignaz Moscheles, Ignacy Jan Paderewski, A. F. Riccius, E. Friedr. Richter, Clara Schumann, Robert Schumann, J. Vogt, Richard Wagner, Ernst Ferdinand Wenzel, Carl Zöllner, and unidentified others. Typed transcription of a letter from Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy to Bradbury (Box 1)
- Photographs (Box 2)
  The Photographs series consists of prints of Bradbury, his wife, Ada Esther Fessender Bradbury, and his piano.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by subject.
  - Photographs of William Bradbury, his wife, Ada Esther Fessender Bradbury, and his piano, Note: One oversize photoprint located in container labeled: Folio 1. (Box 2)
- Clippings, 1962 (Box 2)
  The Clippings series consists of newspaper and magazine articles referring to Bradbury's piano.
  - Newspaper and magazine articles referring to Bradbury's piano (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  The Miscellaneous series consists of artifacts and music related materials of various formats.
  - William B. Bradbury's baton (Box 1)
  - Letter to the editors of The Evening Post by P. T. Barnum referring to expenses paid to Jenny Lind, 1871. Typed from the newspaper clipping. (Box 2)
  - Adams, John S. 5000 Musical Terms: Complete Dictionary. Boston: Oliver Ditson, [1851] (Box 2)
  - Assorted opera librettos (Box 3)
  - Program, Esther, the Beautiful Queen, Riverside Polytechnic High School, Riverside, CA, 1930 (Box 3)